<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: RubyMotion | Scribblings]]></title>
  <link href="http://tech.sunilnkumar.com/blog/categories/rubymotion/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://tech.sunilnkumar.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-22T14:55:50+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://tech.sunilnkumar.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Sunil Kumar]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SSL pinning with Rubymotion]]></title>
    <link href="http://tech.sunilnkumar.com/2014/08/22/ssl-pinning-with-rubymotion"/>
    <updated>2014-08-22T14:50:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://tech.sunilnkumar.com/2014/08/22/ssl-pinning-with-rubymotion</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>To get started with what exactly is SSL pinning and why is this pretty important, please read this <a href="http://blog.lumberlabs.com/2012/04/why-app-developers-should-care-about.html">blog post</a>.</p>

<p>Just to summarize,</p>

<p>A client when making an SSL connection to the server does not check whether the certificate is exactly the one that was uploaded to the server. In browsers, the connections are made to n number of hosts and is obviously unknown prior to making a connection whereas in case of a mobile app, thats not the case. The host to which the connection is to be made is known to the app development team ( certainly in most cases ). Hence we could utilize the power of SSL pinning in mobile apps to add the extra security layer.</p>

<p>To implement SSL pinning, you need the certificate within the app.
I use the BubbleWrap library to make http connections in RubyMotion, but this could well be implemented with something like AFMotion as well. BubbleWrap internally uses the NSUrlConnection to make requests. We use the delegate method of NSUrlConnection ( willSendRequestForAuthenticationChallenge ) to implement the pinning.</p>

<p>I monkey patch ( familiar to Rubyists ) <strong> BubbleWrap::<a href="HTTP::Query">HTTP::Query</a> </strong> to make the necessary changes. Be sure to check that the file type of the certificate is &lsquo;der&rsquo; and its placed in the appropriate directory.</p>

<pre><code>class BubbleWrap::HTTP::Query
  def connection(connection, willSendRequestForAuthenticationChallenge: challenge)
    serverTrust = challenge.protectionSpace.serverTrust
    certificate = SecTrustGetCertificateAtIndex(serverTrust, 0)

    localCertData = (self.localCert)
    serverCertificateData = (SecCertificateCopyData(certificate))

    if(serverCertificateData.to_s == skabberCertData.to_s)
      credential = NSURLCredential.credentialForTrust(serverTrust)
      challenge.sender.useCredential(credential, forAuthenticationChallenge:challenge)
    else
      NSLog("The server's certificate does not match the servers. Cancelling the request.")
      challenge.sender.cancelAuthenticationChallenge(challenge)
    end
  end

  def localCert
    cerPath = NSBundle.mainBundle.pathForResource('something_domain_com', ofType:'der')
    (NSData.dataWithContentsOfFile(cerPath)).to_s
  end
end
</code></pre>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rubymotion: Push Notifications]]></title>
    <link href="http://tech.sunilnkumar.com/2014/03/25/rubymotion-push-notifications"/>
    <updated>2014-03-25T16:24:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://tech.sunilnkumar.com/2014/03/25/rubymotion-push-notifications</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>To setup the app id and ssl certificate and download the ios provisioning profile for push notifications in development mode, this would be a great <a href="http://www.raywenderlich.com/32960/apple-push-notification-services-in-ios-6-tutorial-part-1">article</a> to read on. It worked like a charm for me.</p>

<p>Once thats been done, in your Rubymotion project, add a few extra lines in the Rakefile.</p>

<pre><code>app.name = 'Myapp'
app.identifier = 'com.myapp.development'
app.provisioning_profile = '.environments/Myapp_Develpoment.mobileprovision'
app.entitlements['keychain-access-groups'] = [
  app.seed_id + '.' + app.identifier
]
app.entitlements['aps-environment'] = 'development'
app.entitlements['get-task-allow'] = true
</code></pre>

<p>The <em>app.identifier</em> needs to be the same as the identifier of the app id which was created in the ios development portal.
<em>Myapp_Develpoment.mobileprovision</em> is the provisioning profile generated and downloaded for the app id with identifier &lsquo;com.myapp.development&rsquo;. Both of them are extremely important for the push notifications to work.</p>

<p>In app_delegate.rb, do this.</p>

<pre><code>def application(application, didFinishLaunchingWithOptions:launchOptions)
  ...
  UIApplication.sharedApplication.registerForRemoteNotificationTypes(UIRemoteNotificationTypeAlert | UIRemoteNotificationTypeBadge | UIRemoteNotificationTypeSound)
  true
end

def application(application, didRegisterForRemoteNotificationsWithDeviceToken: device_token)
  NSLog("My token is: %@", device_token)
end

def application(application, didFailToRegisterForRemoteNotificationsWithError: error)
  NSLog(error.inspect)
end
</code></pre>

<p>Next time, when the app is installed on the device it receives an alert requesting permissions to enable push notifications. Also note that the app would ask for permissions only on first time installation. To simulate a first time installation of the app do the following:</p>

<ul>
<li>uninstall the app from the device</li>
<li>switch off &amp; on the device</li>
<li>reset the date to 2 days ahead</li>
<li>switch off and on again</li>
<li>reset the date to even 2 days ahead</li>
<li>switch it off &amp; on for a last time.</li>
</ul>


<p>Install the app and the alert requesting the permission should appear now. ( Got this through some pretty ordinary googling, but it worked pretty well for me :) )</p>

<p>Note down the device_token received in <em>didRegisterForRemoteNotificationsWithDeviceToken</em> method. This is almost like the address of the device to which the push notifications will be sent from the APNS server.</p>

<p>To send a push notification from a Ruby app, I used the grocer gem which worked pretty neat and fast for me. Install the gem &amp; do the following.</p>

<pre><code>require 'grocer'

pusher = Grocer.pusher(
  :certificate =&gt; "ck.pem",
  :passphrase =&gt;  "passphrase",
  :retries =&gt; 3
)

notification = Grocer::Notification.new(
  :device_token  =&gt;   " device token ",
  :alert =&gt;  "My first notification",
  :badge =&gt;   0
)

pusher.push(notification)
</code></pre>

<p>If nothing has been done on the app side to handle these notifications, close the app and send the notifications. They should appear on screen now.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Objective-C Categories into Rubymotion]]></title>
    <link href="http://tech.sunilnkumar.com/2014/02/27/objective-c-categories-into-rubymotion"/>
    <updated>2014-02-27T14:04:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://tech.sunilnkumar.com/2014/02/27/objective-c-categories-into-rubymotion</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>People familiar with developing Ios applications with Objective-C would be quite familiar with using <strong> categories </strong> I suppose.</p>

<p>An Objective-C category allows you to add methods to an existing class — effectively subclassing it without having to deal with the possible complexities of subclassing.</p>

<p>Moving into Rubymotion and using the power of categories is quite well possible for people who have been working with Ruby. <strong>Monkey Patching</strong> ( open an existing class and add your custom code within it ) it quite a familiar task with Rubyists.</p>

<p>Below is an example where I need to add a customized back button for the UINavigationController navigation bar. I need this to be the back button in quite a few View controllers. It would be quite a tedious task to create a button in each VC, hence I create a category file and monkey patch the UIBarButtonItem class to add a new method which returns the customized back button.</p>

<p><em>app/categories/ui_bar_button_item.rb</em></p>

<pre><code>def self.customBackButton(target, action)
  buttonImage = UIImage.imageNamed('arrow.jpeg')
  button = UIButton.buttonWithType(UIButtonTypeCustom)
  button.setImage(buttonImage, forState:UIControlStateNormal)
  button.frame = CGRectMake(0, 0, buttonImage.size.width, buttonImage.size.height)
  button.addTarget(target, action:action, forControlEvents:UIControlEventTouchUpInside)
  customBarItem = UIBarButtonItem.alloc.initWithCustomView(button)
  customBarItem
end
</code></pre>

<p>The view controller which needs to have this customized back button will have this</p>

<pre><code>def viewDidAppear(animated)
  super
  self.navigationItem.leftBarButtonItem = UIBarButtonItem.customBackButton(self.navigationController, 'popViewControllerAnimated:')
end
</code></pre>

<p>This would use Ruby&rsquo;s monkey patching power to create elements in Rubymotion which could be used in the entire application as &amp; when needed.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rubymotion: Chain of Modal segues]]></title>
    <link href="http://tech.sunilnkumar.com/2014/02/06/rubymotion-chain-of-modal-segues"/>
    <updated>2014-02-06T19:02:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://tech.sunilnkumar.com/2014/02/06/rubymotion-chain-of-modal-segues</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>While building my iOS application, I had a user registration process to be implemented. This included the user entering his mobile number, his language details and a few other ( say, miscellaneous ) details. Once he has registered himself he is presented with a table view where a few movies in the language he chose are shown.</p>

<p>The way I went about implementing is that I had a <strong>master_view_controller</strong> which is the initial view controller. The other controllers are</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>mobile_number_view_controller</strong></li>
<li><strong>language_view_controller</strong></li>
<li><strong>miscellaneous_view_controller</strong></li>
<li><strong>movies_view_controller</strong></li>
</ul>


<p>I have segues, <strong>all of type modal</strong>, from the master controller to all other controllers I mentioned above. The segues are of modal type because once the user has submitted each of his details, he doesnt have to care about the particluar detail and is given no option to go back to his previous screen. Its not a like a dig deep type of chain where we could implement the navigation controller. The segues are the follows.</p>

<p>On the left we have the contoller and on the right we have the segue identifier to that controller from the master controller.</p>

<pre><code>master_view_controller:
  mobile_number_view_controller -&gt; msisdnSegue
  language_view_controller -&gt; languageSegue
  miscellaneous_view_controller -&gt; miscellaneousSegue
  movies_view_controller -&gt; moviesSegue
</code></pre>

<p>Also, we have this chain of modal segues.</p>

<pre><code>master_view_controller -&gt; mobile_number_view_controller -&gt; language_view_controller -&gt; miscellaneous_view_controller
</code></pre>

<p>Now in the viewDidAppear delegate of the master controller, we have this check to present the appropriate controller. The details entered by the user in the registration process are saved( we use <strong>motion model</strong> to store the details of the user ). Ofcourse, we dont want a user who has entered his mobile number once to enter it again even if he has opted to quit the app after entering the mobile number. Similarly we dont want him to select his language for the second time during the registration process. We consider all this in the viewDidAppear delegate and decide which contoller to load.</p>

<p>master_view_controller.rb ( This obviously can be implemented better :) )</p>

<pre><code>def viewDidAppear(animated)
  super
  perform_criteria_based_segue
end

def perform_criteria_based_segue
  @user = User.first

  if (not @user) or (not @user.verified_mobile_number)
    performSegueWithIdentifier('msisdnSegue', sender: self)
  end

  elsif not @user.language
    performSegueWithIdentifier('languageSegue', sender: self)
  end

  elsif not @user.miscellaneous_details
    performSegueWithIdentifier('miscellaneousSegue', sender: self)
  end

  else
    performSegueWithIdentifier('moviesSegue', sender: self)
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>Now, suppose the user reached the view where he has to enter his misellaneous details. Once he entered them all he now has to be be shown the table view which list the movies in his language. We have implemented this segue to the movies_view_controller in <strong>viewDidAppear</strong> delegate in the <strong>master_view_controller</strong>. Hence for this to work, the master_view_controller&rsquo;s view will have to appear. For this to happen, the current controller( the i.e, <strong>miscellaneous_view_controller</strong> ) along with all controllers in between the current controller and the master view controller will have to be dismissed ( in our case, its only the <strong>language_view_controller</strong> ).</p>

<p>For this to be done, we have the <strong>dismissViewControllerAnimated(flag, completion:completion_block)</strong> method.</p>

<p>We implement this method in the presented view controller. Here, <strong>miscellaneous_view_controller</strong> is the current presented view controller.</p>

<p>miscellaneous_view_controller.rb</p>

<pre><code>outlet :submitButton, UIButton
ib_action :submit_miscellanous_details

def submit_miscellanous_details
  # Do something here...

  self.view.window.rootViewController.dismissViewControllerAnimated(true, completion:nil)
end
</code></pre>

<p>So in the <strong>miscellaneous_view_controller</strong> controller we have a <em>submitButton</em> which is tied to an ib_action <em>submit_miscellanous_details</em>. On submitting the button, the ib_action is invoked. We do whatever necessary steps is required in the ib_action and then <strong>invoke dismissViewControllerAnimated on the rootViewController( i.e, the master_view_controller )</strong>. When this is done, the presented controllers and all other controllers in the chain of controllers until the presenting controller on whom the dismissViewControllerAnimated method is called ( here, the rootViewController) is also dismissed. The rootViewController or the master_view_controller view appears on screen and the viewDiDAppear delegate will process the rest.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rubymotion: Using ProgressHud while making Http calls]]></title>
    <link href="http://tech.sunilnkumar.com/2014/01/24/rubymotion-using-progresshud-while-making-http-calls"/>
    <updated>2014-01-24T20:04:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://tech.sunilnkumar.com/2014/01/24/rubymotion-using-progresshud-while-making-http-calls</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With Rubymotion, there are quite a few methods to indicate activities. What I have used here is the MBProgressBarHud to indicate an ongoing activity ( an http call in progress )</p>

<h4>controller/msisdn_view_controller.rb</h4>

<pre><code>outlet :submitButton, UIButton
ib_action :submit_mobile_number  #The submit button on event ‘Touch Up Inside’ invokes the action submit_mobile_number

def viewDidLoad
  @hud = MBProgressHUD.alloc.initWithWindow(UIApplication.sharedApplication.keyWindow)
  self.view.addSubview(@hud)
end

def submit_mobile_number(sender)
  msisdn = self.msisdnTextField.text
  prepare_for_submission
  User.registration msisdn, do
    after_submission
  end
end

def prepare_for_submission
  @hud.labelText = "Provisioning"
  @hud.show(true)
  self.view.userInteractionEnabled = false
end

def after_submission
  @hud.labelText = "Completed";
  @hud.hide(true)
  performSegueWithIdentifier('submission_segue', sender: self)
end
</code></pre>

<h4>models/user.rb</h4>

<pre><code>def self.registration(msisdn, &amp;callback)
  ...
  url = 'some_url'
  BW::HTTP.get(url) do |response|
    callback.call
    ...
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>As you could see from the code above, in the viewDidLoad delegate we initiate an MBProgressHUD instance and add it as a subview to the UIView. This is done in the viewDidLoad delegate.</p>

<p>Before the call to <strong>registration</strong> ( the User model method which makes an http connection ) is made, the <strong>prepare_for_submission</strong> method displays the hud. The <strong>after_submission</strong> method is passed as a callback block to the <strong>registration</strong> method. On completion of the http request, this block is executed which hides the hud and performs the segue to present the next controller.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
